Guide to the Joseph Libbey Folsom Collection
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Joseph Libbey Folsom collection
1849-1855
WA MSS S-2394
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.02
(6 boxes)
Correspondence, documents, bills and receipts and writings by or relating to Joseph Libbey Folsom. The collection appears to have been formed by the executors of his estate, the San Francisco firm Halleck, Peachy & Billings. The correspondence contains approximately twenty letters to and from Joseph Folsom. These include correspondence with Suydam, Reed & Co., lawyers in New York who represented Folsom in a legal battle over land in California. There are approximately 150 letters to and from Halleck, Peachy & Billings. Principal correspondents are Peter Morris and James B. Wilson, who write about troubles with squatters, miners, and woodcutters on Folsom estate land. There are approximately 160 leases, many of them duplicates, for property in San Francisco owned by Folsom. The Bills and Receipts, most of them made out to Folsom, record both personal and professional purchases, including daguerreotypes, laundry services, materials used in constructing various buildings. The writings consist of two miscellaneous one page essays, probably by Folsom.
Folsom, Joseph Libbey, 1817-1855
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Lindley Eberstadt, 1959.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
JOSEPH LIBBEY FOLSOM (1817-1855)
Joseph Libbey Folsom was born May 19, 1817, in New Hampshire. He was a graduate of West Point and went to California in 1846 as Captain and Assistant Quartermaster of Stevenson's Regiment of New York Volunteers. After the Mexican War, he settled in San Francisco and was the Collector of the Port of San Francisco. He invested in real estate in San Francisco and beyond, notably purchasing rights to William A. Leidesdorff's large estate, the Rancho Rio de los Americanos in Sacramento County. Folsom died in San Jose, California on July 19, 1855, at the age of 38. At the time of his death, he was developing Leidesdorff estate land into town lots, and the resulting town, Folsom, was named in his honor. The executor of his estate was the San Francisco law firm Halleck, Peachy & Billings.
Scope and Contents
The Joseph Libbey Folsom Collection consists of correspondence, documents, bills and receipts and writings by and relating to Joseph Libbey Folsom, a California pioneer who invested in real estate in San Francisco and beyond soon after gold was discovered in California. The collection appears to have been formed by the executors of his estate, the San Francisco firm Halleck, Peachy & Billings, as it includes both material belonging to Folsom shortly before his death in 1855 as well as material addressed to the executors after his death. The collection is organized into four series: Correspondence, Documents, Bills and Receipts and Writings, and spans the dates 1849-1862.
Series I, Correspondence, is organized into three subseries: Joseph Libbey Folsom; Halleck, Peachy & Billings; and Others. The correspondence is organized alphabetically in each subseries; individuals or businesses with more than three letters are listed alphabetically. Folsom's correspondence (including drafts of letters from Folsom) consists of about twenty letters. Among the letters are six between Folsom and Suydam, Reed & Co., lawyers in New York who represented Folsom during his legal battle with Anna Maria Spark, the mother of William A. Leidesdorff, from whom Folsom purchased the rights to Leidesdorff's estate in California. The Halleck, Peachy & Billings subseries contains approximately 150 letters to (and occasional drafts of letters from) the firm. This correspondence concerns Folsom's legal affairs before his death and the disposition of the estate. Principal correspondents with Halleck, Peachy & Billings include Peter Morris and James B. Wilson. Morris purchased land from the Folsom estate and writes of troubles with squatters and miners encroaching on his lots. Wilson, apparently an administrator of the estate in Folsom, also writes of squatters and problems with woodcutters operating illegally on the estate lands.
Series II, Documents, is organized into two subseries: Leases and Other Papers. There are approximately 160 leases for property in San Francisco owned by Folsom, many of them duplicates. Each lease carries the name of the renter, address, and amount of the rent. Some of the renters are Chinese men, some are women; some leases include other information, such as the one for Samuel Hort which has a schedule of furniture included. The leases for 1851 are made out as indentures between Anna Maria Spark of Saint Croix, Danish West Indies, by her Attorney-in-fact Joseph L. Folsom. The leases have been arranged alphabetically, by name of renter. Those names represented by more than three leases are listed individually.
The Other Papers housed at the end of the series include an account of sale of "grey domestics" (plain cotton cloth) from Leidesdorff's estate, costs claimed in the case of Folsom vs. Sands & Lewis, and proposals to the executors to purchase land in Folsom and on the Rancho Rio de Los Americanos.
Series III, Financial Papers, is organized into Bills and Receipts and Other Financial Papers. The Bills and Receipts are organized into two sections: Joseph Libbey Folsom and Others, and then arranged alphabetically by the name of the individual or business issuing the bill or receipt. Individuals or businesses are listed individually if they are represented by more than three items. The Bills and Receipts record both personal and professional purchases, including daguerreotypes from Hamilton and Starr, the services of R. W. Laine, a night watchman, laundry service by D. Landis, materials used in constructing various buildings Folsom owned in San Francisco, and receipts from the hotel Tehama House, also in San Francisco. Other papers include canceled checks written by both Folsom and the executors.
Series IV, Writings consists of two miscellaneous one page essays, probably by Folsom.
Real property -- California; California -- Gold discoveries; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Commerce; Leases -- California; Receipts (financial records); Folsom, Joseph Libbey, 1817-1855; Morris, Peter, fl. 1857; Wilson, James B.; Halleck, Peachy & Billings (San Francisco, Calif.); Suydam, Reed & Co
- Correspondence, 1849-1860; Series I; 0.64; (1.5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Correspondence is organized into three subseries: Joseph Libbey Folsom, Halleck, Peachy & Billings, and Others. The correspondence is organized alphabetically in each subseries, with individuals or businesses with more than three letters listed individually.
  - FOLSOM, JOSEPH LIBBEY
    - "B" general, 1851-52 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "C-H" general, 1851-52 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Halleck, Peachy & Billings, 1852 Jul 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Rogers, L., 1851 Feb 5 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Smith, William L., 1851 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Suydam, Reed & Co., 1851-54 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Tobin & Duncan, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Webb, Henry, 1852 Jun 10 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified, 1849 Sep 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - HALLECK, PEACHY & BILLINGS
    - "A" general, 1851-52 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "B" general, 1852-56 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bradley, L., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - "C" general, 1853-[60] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Catlin, A. P., 1857-60 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "D" general, 1856-58 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - "E" general, 1856-57 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - "F" general, 1855-60 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Forrest, Sallie L., 1855-57 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - "G" general, 1856 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "H" general, 1853-60 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Hartsaugh, D. B., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Hoskins, E. D., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Janson Bond & Co., 1856 Feb 6 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Lewis, O. C., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Livermore, H. G., 1857 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - "M" general, 1856-57 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Morris, Peter, 1857 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "N-R" general, 1855-57, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - "S" general, 1856-57 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Smith, William L., 1855-56 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Sunderland, Thomas, 1856-57, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Suydam, Reed & Co., 1858 Feb 19 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - "T" general, 1857 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - "W" general, 1852-60 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Wilson, James B., [1855]-57 (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
    - Unidentified, 1859, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Empty folder, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - OTHERS
    - Correspondence, 1849-55 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Documents, 1850-1859; Series II; 0.8; (2 boxes)
  Series II, Documents, is organized into two subseries: Leases and Other Papers. The subseries are organized alphabetically; those names represented by more than three leases are listed individually.
  - LEASES
    - Ackley, J. T., 1851 Aug 29 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - "B" general, 1851-53 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - "C" general, 1851 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Engelvaart, John and John Bosboom, 1851 Nov 16 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - "F" general, 1851-53 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "H" general, 1851-55 (Box 2, Folder 45-47)
    - Heddon, James T., 1851-52 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Hobe, George J., 1852-53 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - "I-J" general, 1850-51 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Jackson, William, 1853 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - "K" general, 1851-55 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "L" general, 1851-55 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    - "M" general, 1851-55 (Box 3, Folder 54-56)
    - "N-O" general, 1853-55 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - "P" general, 1853-54 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - "Q-R" general, 1851-55 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    - "S" general, 1851-55 (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
    - "T" general, 1852-55 (Box 3, Folder 62-63)
    - "V" general, 1851-52 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - "W" general, 1851-54 (Box 4, Folder 65-66)
  - OTHER PAPERS
    - Account of sale of grey domestics from Leidesdorff's estate, 1850 Aug 17 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Articles of agreement between Folsom and J. H. Atkinson [to build a safe], n.y. Jun 5 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Costs claimed in the case Folsom vs. Sands & Lewis, 1852 Mar 31 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Proposals to purchase land in Folsom and on Rancho Rio De Los Americanos, 1856-57 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Settlement of accounts of Folsom's executors, 1859 Mar 9 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Subdivision of 50 "Vara" Lots, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Miscellaneous documents, 1853-57, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 73)
      Stored also in: Oversize, box 6, folder 132
- Financial Papers, 1850-1862; Series III; 0.66; (1.5 boxes)
  Series III, Financial Papers, is organized into Bills and Receipts and Other Financial Papers. The Bills and Receipts are organized by those belonging to Joseph Libbey Folsom and those belonging to Others. They are arranged alphabetically, with more than three items for an individual or business listed individually.
  - BILLS AND RECEIPTS
    - Folsom, Joseph Libbey
      - "A" general, 1851-52 (Box 4, Folder 74)
      - "B" general, 1851-52, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 75)
      - Barker & Paddock, 1852 (Box 4, Folder 76)
      - Blackburn & Thompson, 1851-52, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 77)
      - Brittingham & Co., 1851 (Box 4, Folder 78)
      - Brown, J. H., 1852 (Box 4, Folder 79)
      - Buckley, John P., 1851-52 (Box 4, Folder 80)
      - "C" general, 1851-55, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 81)
      - California Courier, 1851 (Box 4, Folder 82)
      - Cany, E., 1850-51 (Box 4, Folder 83)
      - Crowne & Travers, 1852 (Box 4, Folder 84)
      - "D" general, 1851-52, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 85)
      - Dorr, R. S., 1851 (Box 4, Folder 86)
      - "E" general, 1852, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 87)
      - Easterly, House and Ship Plumber & Tin and Sheet Iron, 1851-52, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 88)
      - Eddy, William M., 1851-52, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 89)
      - Endicott, Greene & Oakes, 1851 (Box 4, Folder 90)
      - "F" general, 1851-52 (Box 4, Folder 91)
      - Frank Baker, 1852 (Box 4, Folder 92)
      - "G" general, 1851-53 (Box 4, Folder 93)
      - G.O. Whitney, 1851-52 (Box 4, Folder 94)
      - Genella, Joseph, 1851-52 (Box 4, Folder 95)
      - "H" general, 1851-52, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 96)
      - Halleck, Peachy & Billings, 1851-52, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 97)
      - "J" general, 1851-52 (Box 5, Folder 98)
      - J. & C. Grant, 1852, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 99)
      - John S. Eagan, 1851-52 (Box 5, Folder 100)
      - "K" general, 1851-52 (Box 5, Folder 101)
      - "L" general, 1851-52 (Box 5, Folder 102)
      - Laine, R. W., 1852 (Box 5, Folder 103)
      - Landis, D., 1851-52, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 104)
      - "M" general, 1851-52, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 105)
        Stored also in: Oversize, box 6, folder 133
      - Macondray & Co., 1851 (Box 5, Folder 106)
      - Naylor, Peter, 1852 Jul 17 (Box 5, Folder 107)
      - Neagle, William, 1851 (Box 5, Folder 108)
      - "O" general, 1851-52 (Box 5, Folder 109)
      - Onderdonk, G., 1851-52 (Box 5, Folder 110)
      - "P" general, 1851-54 (Box 5, Folder 111)
        Stored also in: Oversize, box 6, folder 134
      - "R" general, 1851-53 (Box 5, Folder 112)
      - Roby, William, 1851 (Box 5, Folder 113)
      - "S" general, 1851-60, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 114)
      - Sanford, F. C., 1851 (Box 5, Folder 115)
      - Sirick & Co., 1852 (Box 5, Folder 116)
      - Smith & Wells, 1851-52 (Box 5, Folder 117)
      - Starkweather, McClenachon & Co., 1851 (Box 5, Folder 118)
      - "T" general, 1851-53 (Box 5, Folder 119)
      - Tehama House, 1853-54 (Box 5, Folder 120)
      - "V" general, 1851-52 (Box 5, Folder 121)
      - "W" general, 1852-53 (Box 5, Folder 122)
      - Wilson's Exchange, 1852-55, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 123)
      - Wyman & Huntington, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 124)
      - "Y-Z" general, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 125)
    - Others
      - Bills and receipts, 1851-52, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 126)
  - OTHER FINANCIAL PAPERS
    - Canceled checks, 1854 (Box 5, Folder 127)
    - Canceled checks, 1855-62 (Box 5, Folder 128)
    - Rates of wharfage, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 129)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1851-52 (Box 5, Folder 130)
      Stored also in: Oversize, box 6, folder 135
- Writings, n.d.; Series IV
  - Miscellaneous writings, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 131)
- Oversize, 0.92; (1 box)
  Oversize contains oversize materials from series I and III, arranged in box order.
  - Miscellaneous documents (in Series I), 1856-57, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 132)
  - "M" general (in Series III), 1851-52, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 133)
  - "P" general (in Series III), 1851-54 (Box 6, Folder 134)
  - Miscellaneous papers (in Series III), 1851-52 (Box 6, Folder 135)